Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1830-1839., 55 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James K. Marshall, Leeds Manor, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 9 May 1834., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Discusses sale of his [James K. Marshall's] land; inform Edward [Carrington Marshall] that he [John Marshall] is pleased with the terms on which he has not rented Mont Blanc; will not leave for the country till July when he will visit [Fauquier White Sulphur] Springs; the May wheat has been injured by frost.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 3 December 1834., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Questions him about the defeat of [John] Hardin at the battle of the St. Joseph reported in his [John Marshall's] Life of Washington; asks him to check with Mr. [Jared] Sparks if it was really fought on Paint Creek; discusses the elections of the Virginia legislature; mentions Martin van Buren.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [?], 4 April 1835., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Describes how George Washington convinced him to run for Congress in 1798.
        Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to J. Y. Campbell, Uniontown, Pennsylvania, 4 April 1835., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Would have written upon his return from Washington, but was seriously injured in the stage; cannot find and send him a letter in George Washington's hand as requested; does enclose a military appointment of 1799 with Washington's signature.
      - Henry Potter, Fayetteville, [North Carolina], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 20 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Hopes his injury will not be permanent; fears the loss to the nation if he resigns; has "cleared the decks for the great legal conflict."
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to [?], [n.d.]., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Discusses arrangements regarding the acquisition of Mrs. [?] Kennon's [?] negroes.
        Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia], to Charles Lee, Fredericksburg, [Virginia], [n.d.]., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Discusses Mr. [?] Warden's and Mr. Washington's and Brooke's suits which he [Charles Lee] agreed to look into for him [John Marshall].
      - Notes written in French in Marshall's hand describing the origins of the English colonies in America, [n.d.]., 8 pages. AL. (Box-folder 4:6)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia?], to [?] Cary and [?] Lea, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]," [n.d]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        A friend from the West has pointed out an error in his [John Marshall's] manuscript which he would like to correct as follows: "v.2 p.207 1.27 at "Chilicothe".. ."not Chilicothe on the Scioto in Ohio, but ... an old Indian village then standing about seventy-five miles rather East of North from Cincinnati...
      - [John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia] to "my dear son" [Thomas Marshall?, Fauquier County, Virginia], [n.d.]., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Has had some difficulty weighing and selling his Parkinson breed of hogs because they were too large and their meat is not sweet enough; discusses purchases made for him, Mary, Fanny Burwell, and Maria Willis according to his directions; is surprised at the magnitude of his [Thomas Marshall's] debts; lectures on paying them off.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, [Richmond, Virginia] to John Henry, [n.p.], [n.d.]., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Informs him that his rent for the Campbell [?] land belonging to his [John Marshall's] father's estate is due.
        Rush Rhees Library, University of Rochester.
      - [John Marshall, Washington, D.C.], to "The President of the United States." [Washington, D.C.], [n.d.]., 1 page. Pst of AL. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Accepts the President's invitation to dinner next Thursday at four.
      - J[ohn] R[andolph] of R[oanoke] to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.?], [n.d.]., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 4:6)
        Discusses the last letter which he [John Randolph Roanoke] sent to him [John Marshall].
  - Correspondence and Papers of Relatives and Descendents of John Marshall, 1797-1916., 17 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Mrs. [Eliza J. (Ambler) Brent] Carrington, Mount Vernon, [Virginia], to Mrs. [Nancy (Ambler)] Fisher, n.p., 22 November 1797 [?]., 12 pages. Cy. of L. Incomplete. (Box-folder 5:1)
      [Both are sisters of John Marshall's wife, Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall.]. Discusses her and her husband's, [Colonel Edward Carrington], visit with the Washington family at Mount Vernon and the impending delivery of Mrs. L. Custis Lewis's first child; describes their visit to the new national capitol on the Potomac; writes of their return to Mount Vernon and of their diversions there, which include hunting deer and taking care of the new baby, or "the pretty little stranger"; describes a chambermaid and other servants; comments upon domestic fashions and describes the furnishings of the mansion, which concludes with a description of the estate with its greenhouse and gardens, and of their host's [George Washington] treatment of his many visitors.
      Including TCy of ALS. 6 pages.
    - Mary M[arshall, daughter of John Marshall], Honey Wood, [Fauquier County, Virginia?], to her mother, 1 February 1811., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia]. Hopes that she will send for her in April, although her Aunt [Elizabeth (Marshall) Colston] says that it is unlikely; Uncle [Rawleigh Colston] is upset at all the letters she is sending, and refuses to pay postage on them; wanted to buy muslin in Martinsburg to make her a handkerchief and a cap for sister [?]; discusses her French lessons with her tutor, Mr. LeRoy, and incidents of his exasperation with Tom [Thomas M. Colston], Tom [Thomas] Marshall[a cousin], and Rawleigh [a cousin, Raleigh T. Colston], Cousin Edward [Colston] cruelly takes delight in telling her that she will not be able to go home until fall, and "Uncle says he does not think you love me enough to ... send for me..."
    - J[ames Markham] Marshall, Happy Creek, [Frederick County, Virginia], to his nephew, Martin P. Marshall, Washington, Mason County, Kentucky, 11 April 1822., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Has already conveyed his [James Markham Marshall's] undiscarded half of land at the forks of the Licking [Fauquier County?]; no longer has an interest in it, but will convey the novelty to him [Martin P. Marshall] at any time; "lament[s] extremely the misunderstanding between yourself and Tom..."; Lucy Marshall is in Fauquier [County].
    - Tho[ma]s Marshall, "Westover," [Charles City County, Virginia], to "Mother" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, [Virginia], 28 February 1824., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Was lucky he came down on Tuesday, For he found his daughter, Nancy, ill, which has caused them to postpone their return to Weyanoke, [Virginia]; has cone a little transferring for Father; has been playing chess with Mr. [?] James? Taylor of Norfolk; instructs Agnes [his daughter] to attend to her studies in Richmond; hopes her [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall] trip to Chickahominy did not fatigue her.
    - Edward C[arrington] Marshall, Cambridge, [Massachusetts], to Mary W[illis (Ambler)] Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 8 November 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Mentions changes made in the college government at Harvard College; complains of college life - "probably no life is so uninteresting to others as that of a merely literary man. An indolent collegian especially has nothing to say for himself..."; mentions his classes: Electricity, Astronomy, and Moral Philosophy; describes his "chums," [?] Turner, [?J Bonaparte, a nephew of the Emperor, [?] Cheves, son of Langdon Cheves, [?] Bruce, of Halifax County, and his cousin [?] Birchett; discusses dining arrangements at Harvard: "We have a large table, confined to southerners, and what are called gentlemen Yankees"; looks forward with great anxiety to graduating in ten months.
    - Mary W[illis (Ambler)] Marshall's will, [ca. 1830]., 2 pages. AD. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Most of her bank stock is to be distributed to her children and their children, although she leaves five bank shares for her "faithful friend and house keeper Mrs. Francis Martyr" and her daughter Anne and ten dollars a year in perpetuity to the school for orphan children established by the Ladies of Richmond.
      Including TCy of AD. 1 page.
    - J[ohn] Marshall Jr., Mont Blanc, to Charles Fenton Mercer, Washington, [D.C.], 16 February 1832., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Discusses the publication of the last Census and its effects on Congressional apportionment; discusses railroads and canals; writes of abolition in Loudoun and Fauquier Counties, [Virginia].
    - Edw[ar]d C.[arrington] Marshall, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], to Mary [(Marshall)] Harvie, Richmond, Virginia, 29 June 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Informs her of her brother [Thomas Marshall's] accident in Baltimore and of his impending death; Father [John Marshall] has rallied from his severe cold, but does not continue to improve; he has taken cold again, is feeble, and has no appetite; he apprehends the worst.
    - J[ames] K[eith] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Claudia H. [(Burwell)] Marshall, Leeds Manor, Fauquier [County, Virginia], 6 December 1840., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Describes the weather; Mrs. [?] Mayo has the gout; Mary Archer and family are well; Margaret and Agnes Douthat are with her; Robert Pickett said nothing about paying back the loan; discusses his daughters' lessons under Mr. [?] Daley; gives directions for the farm; writes of General [Jaquelin] Harvie; discusses arrangements for her Christmas trip and for her slaves; asks about his daughters Claudia and Maria Willis.
      Including TCy of ALS. 2 pages. Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
    - A[lexander] J[ames] Marshall, Warrenton, [Virginia], to Daniel Webster, n.p., 24 April 1841. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Writes a favorable recommendation for Dr. J. W. Leach who has resided in Fauquier County a few years and practiced medicine "with success and usefulness," but who desires to move to the city to "improve his fortunes and educate his children."
      Including ANS from D[aniel] W[ebster], n.p., n.d. to Mr. Bell, n.p., recommending A.J. Marshall "son [nephew] of the late Ch[ief] Jus[tice]& a very reputable man."
    - Edward Colston, [n.p.] to Dr. [?] Robinson, [n.p.], 27 December 1845., 1 page. Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Handwritten copy [by Alice Colston?]; tells him to draw on his [Edward Colston's] money at the Valley Bank. of Winchester and send $10 to Raleigh Edward at Lexington and the rest to W[illiam] Leigh.
      Including Cy of ADS, (in same hand); 12 October 1840, Elizabeth Colston's will; bequeaths her slaves and other worldly possessions to her children and grandchildren. 4 pages.
    - United States of America. Passport issued to W. W. Harvie, 4 April 1858. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Includes an engraving of a spread-eagled American bald eagle bearing a lyre with the motto "Nunc Sidera Ducit" surrounded by thirteen stars; also bears the seal of the Department of State; the passport stamps show that Harvie visited France, Belgium, Austria, Switzerland, Holland, Italy, Spain, Algeria, Rome, Naples, and Germany from May 1858 to March 1859.
    - J[ames] K[eith] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Claudia (Burwell) Marshall, Fauquier County, Virginia?], 7 January 1861., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Describes railroad travel in Virginia; discusses his visit in Richmond; mentions Col. [?] Mason's and G[overn]or [John B.] Floyd's efforts at arousing sentiment for immediate secession; mentions prices of railroad tickets.
    - Secretary of War of the Confederate States of America L[eroy] P[ope] Walker certifies that Frank G. Rutfin has been appointed a Captain in the Subsistence Department of the Provisional Army, 29 June 1861., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Including PDS. 1 page. Acceptance and oath of Frank G. Rutfin signed in Richmond before James Ellett, Notary Public, on 19 August 1861.
    - An Appeal addressed to the Ladies of Virginia and signed by Mrs. M. H. Mactarland, Mrs. Frank G. Ruttin [Ellen S. (Harvie) Ruffin], Miss Catherine H. Myers, Mrs. F. E. Nelson, Mrs. N[?] B. Gwathney, and Mrs. M. Stewart Walker, asking for their assistance in relief work among wounded soldiers, [ca. August 1861]., 2 pages. AD. (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Receipt for taxes paid by Frances G. Rutfin at Richmond, [Virginia], on lands in Chesterfield County, Virginia, 5 April 1866., 1 page. PDS. (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Albert J. Beveridge, Beverly Farms, Massachusetts, to Ellen Harvie Wade, Richmond, Virginia. 29 January 1916., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Thanks her for writing to him in Miss [?] Harvie's behalf and for granting him an extension; the publishers will finish the reproducing within three weeks at which time he will return the miniture [sic] to her aunt; distressed to hear of Anne Harvie's death.
      Including Pst of ALS. 1 page. Incomplete.
  - Correspondence and Papers of Other Individuals, 1771-1844., 14 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Indenture signed by Thomas, Lord Fairfax leasing lands in the Manor of, Leeds in Fauquier County, Virginia to John Dearing, 30 November 1771., 2 pages. Pst of ADS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Including Pst of ADS. 2 pages. 30 November 1771. Another indenture signed by Fairfax leasing land in the Manor of Leeds to William Seth.
    - Governor Patrick Henry of Virginia grants to George Washington, assignee of Baynes Carter, a 148 acre tract of land on Reed Creek in Henry County, Virginia, 21 November 1780., 1 page. PD. Incomplete. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Governor P[atrick] Henry appoints Richard Richards Ensign of the 4th Company of the Sussex Regiment of Virginia militia, 1 July 1785., 1 page. Pst of PDS. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Land grant to Walter Graham and John James for land in Fayette County, [Virginia] [West Virginia], signed by Governor Beverley Randolph, 2[?] December 1789., 1 page. Pst of D.S. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Bill of Lading for 311 barrels of flour to Norfolk, [Virginia], on the ship Dolphin, 29 June 1793., 1 page. Pst of PDS. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - S[aint] G[eorge] [?] Tucker, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to John Page, Rosewell, [Virginia], 27 February 1801., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Does not view the consequences of their success in the election [of 1800] in as favorable a light as he [John Page] does; speculates on what would have been the result of the election had there been no contest between the "two Gentlemen who stood highest" [Jefferson and Burr], and if [Charles Cotesworter] Pin[c]key or [John] Adams had opposed Jefferson; speculates on the "presumption" of the Federalist view that should "no election... take place, Mr. Adams is, under the Constitution, to continue in office until a successor be appointed; that is until the next election of course"; says appointments of John Marshall as Chief Justice, seventeen new judges, and [?] Bayard "the most unacceptable man that could be sent to the French republic," nominated as minister plenipotentiary -- all extend the influence of the Federalists and throw an obstacle in the way of Jefferson's administration; adds a few lines typical of what he sees as Federalist sentiment; and writes of their friendship.
    - John Randolph of Roanoke, Roanoke, [Virginia], to his nephew, T[heodorick] Tudor Randolph, Harvard College, Cambridge, [Massachusetts], 29 August 1813., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Since he [John Randolph] is not long for this world, is anxious to settle his affairs; "should you decide upon a settlement south of Philad[elphi]a(which God forbid) I am desirous that you should fix yourself as soon as possible on the plantation below the mouth of little Roanoke...[Bizarre Plantation?];" his [John Randolph's] infirmity has prevented him from giving the estate the requisite attention, and it is much encumbered with debt; discusses his failing health: "there is something radically a miss in the system. The machine cannot last much longer."
    - Captain George Hunter, commander of the 60th Regiment of the Virginia Militia, appoints John E. Barker Sergeant and Officer of the Guard detailed to conduct 60th Regiment absentees back to camp, 3 October 1814., 1 page. Pst of ANS. (Box-folder 5:2)
    - John Randolph of Roanoke, Farmville, [Virginia], to [?], 23 April 1817., 1 page. Pst of ALS. Fragment. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Thanks him for compliance with his request "thru our mutual friend Mr. John Marshall"; will write soon; sends paper for Capt. Brown.
    - H[enry] Clay, Ashland, [Kentucky?] to James F. Conover [?], Cincinnati, Ohio, 3 August 1831., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Comments on events in Washington which instill "deep regret and surprize"; mentions the election in Kentucky; says the antimasonic excitement will likely be "troublesome" but he will not get involved in it; has not heard from Mr. [?] Hammond for a long time but does not distrust him but disagrees over the issue of the representation of Ohio in the Baltimore Convention; glad to hear of his [James F. Conover] professional prospects.
    - F[rancis] S[cott] Key, U[nited] S[tates] A[ttorney], D[istrict of] C[olumbia], [Washington, D.C.], to J. E. Burfoot, Richmond, Virginia, [19 May 1833-1835?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Discusses the case of [?] Randolph being heard by U.S. District Court Judge [Philip P.] Barbour.
    - Edward Anderson [?], Richmond, Virginia, to James P. Preston, Christianburg, [Virginia?], 9 July 1835., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Chief Justice [John] Marshall died in Philadelphia last Monday, perfectly in his senses to the last; the news reached here only this morning, and his remains at 4 p.m.; describes the funeral procession.
    - H[enry] Lee, Paris, [France], to B[enjamin] W. Leigh, [n.p.], 28 August 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Encloses the diploma of the historical Institute of France which just elected John Marshall a member on his [Henry Lee's] recommendation; describes Marshall's election to that society.
    - W [?] H [?] Rooke, [T?] Hill [?], to Eliza McDonald, Marietta, Georgia, 15 April 1844., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Is happy about her recovery; quotes Shakespeare; describes his own health; writes of his political campaigning in King and Queen, King William, and Hanover counties, [Virginia]; describes her old neighborhood and farm, now occupied by Fleetwood Academy; discusses George Haskins situation, mentioning his lack of slaves; gossips about affairs in King and Queen County; discusses the unusual weather; tells an Irish joke; discusses [Henry] Clay's tariff.
  Series 2: Printed Material, Poems, and Charts
- Printed Material, Poems, and Charts, 1789-1959, n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Letters of George Washington, James Madison and Edward Everett submitted to various newspapers in which American Freemasony is attacked and defended, 25 September 1789, 24 January 1832, 29 June 1833., 3 items. NCls. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - The Home Life of Chief-Justice Marshall by C.N.S. in the Richmond Dispatch, reprinted from the Louisville Age. Reminiscences of Marshall's personality, treatment of his wife and servants, and his leisure activities, 18 April 1879., 3 pages. NCl. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Articles describing various statues of Chief Justice John Marshall, 6 August 1881, 1925, and undated., 3 items. NCls. (Box-folder 5:3)
    One was a wax portrait in basso-relievo donated by Horace Edwin Hayden to the Virginia Historical Society in 1881; another was the bronze monument by W.W. Story which stands on the terrace of the U. S. Capitol; the members of the Marshall family who attended the dedication of this statue are listed in a third article.
  - Anonymous poem attacking John Marshall's decision in the Supreme Court case of Cohen vs. Virginia; the author, a proponent of state sovereignty, threatens that Marshall will be replaced by the Judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, Spencer Roane, [May-June 1821]., 2 pages. Pst. of Poem. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Lines written for a lady's album, [February 1829?]., 1 page. Poem. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Poem written on the request of a lady to inscribe his name in her autograph book.
    Including TCy of AL. 1 page.
  - Handwritten copy [ca. 1900] by Mrs. John K. Mason of a poem by John Marshall entitled From the Chameleon to the Mocking Bird,[1829?]., 3 pages. Cy of Poem. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Poem honors the splendid singing voice of Miss Eliza Lambert, the sister of Richmond's Mayor William Lambert.
    Westover Library, Arlington, Virginia.
  - Poem by Innis Randolph, [1869?]., 1 page. Poem. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Lines on the occasion of the raising of the bronze statue of Chief Justice Marshall, at Richmond in 1869(?) - while Brig. Gen'l Terry was in command of 'District No. 1'- which included the state of Virginia.
  - Case of Chief Justice Marshall, [1831]., 2 pages. Pst of Article in Volume 9 of the American Journal of Medical Sciences. PM. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Discusses tr. Physick's operation on John Marshall.
  - Penciled note describing order of John Marshall's funeral procession and other arrangements for the day, 9 July 1835., 2 pages. AN. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Lists his pall-bearers: Henry St. George Tucker, John B. Clapton, Benj[amin] W [?] Leigh, Tho[ma]s Rutherford, Cha[rle]s Copland, Rob[er]t Popllard, Chapman Johnson, Robert Stanard, [?] Scott, and [?] D. Wren[?]; also lists the Marshalls: Col. Geo[rge] M. Carrington, [?] General [William] Lambert, General [?] Peyton, and Col. Armistead.
  - Account of John Marshall's 1831 operation by Doctor Physick written by J.[?] Randolph, M.D. and printed in A Memoir of Dr. Physick,[1839]., 6 pages. Pst of PM. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Mentions the results of an autopsy on Marshall's body after his death in 1835.
    Library of the College of Physicians, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
  - Chief Justice Marshall and his Work, by Robert H. Hughes, 1887., 24 pages. PM. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Published by the Reformed Church Publication Board in Philadelphia. The Centennial Address delivered before the Franklin and Marshall College of Lancaster, Pennsylvania on 14 June 1887.
  - Genealogical chart of the Marshall Family by W. M. Paxton, [ca. 1890]., 2 pages. Pst of PM. Including index. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - The Political Ideas of John Marshall, autographed by the author, Saul K. Padover, in the Spring 1959 issue of Social Research, 1959. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Subsequently published by McGraw-Hill in a 1960 book, Fountain of Freedom.
  - Copy of an address by Alfred Harris Bright entitled John Marshall,n.d., 10 pages. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Minnesota Historical Society, St. Paul, Minnesota.
  Series 3: Prints, Engravings, and Artifacts
- Prints, Engravings, and Artifacts, 1825-1937., 8 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Color lithographs of two portraits of John Marshall., 2 items. Lithographs. Color. (Box-folder 5:4)